Will you smoke with me, Da Vinci?
要跟我一起抽 _芬奇?
Well, that depends on what's in the pipe.
那要看Y面b的是什N了
It is a mixture of tobacco and black hellebore
草混著}Q玫瑰
and is rumored to induce visions
f可人a生幻X
and summon demons.
召境耗
Well, I believe in neither.
全是o稽之
Then why do you struggle so hard to keep both at bay?
那你又何必@N努力克制呢?
History is a lie that has been honed like a weapon
v史就如同武器一般 被那些意欲掩w真相的人
by people who have suppressed the truth.
肆意改 只剩e言
The knowledge you are destined to learn
你注定W那些
will upend the established order of things.
覆事物既定秩序的知R
How could you possibly know that?
你怎N知道?
You have heard the phrase 'Time is a river'?
你^ 'rg是一l河流'吧?
Yes.
是的
What most fail to grasp is that the river is circular.
但大多等]有理解到 @l河流是h形的
One man's death opens a doorway
每人的死亡都_⒘
to the birth of the next.
另一人重生的大T
Would you like to know how
你想知道@道重生之T
this particular doorway opened?
是如何_⒌?
Yes.
想
Be forewarned, then.
先提醒你一句
Some doorways lead into darkness.
K非所有大T都通向光明
Out you go, boy. Get on with you!
走吧 孩子 把衣服穿上!
Go on! Go on!
走吧! 快走!
Cicco!
奇高!
- What day is it today?  - Palm Sunday.
- 今天星期?  - 棕爸魅(突罟前的星期日)
Oh, balls.
死
The Duchess and your children are already at the church.
夫人和您的子民都已在教堂了
Could you round me up some coddled eggs?
o我煮些u蛋吧
I have a beastly hangover and my bowels are in a tumble.
我宿醉得害 肚子Y翻江倒海的
I'll be dressed in but a minute.
我很快就穿好
At ease, people, I've arrived!
大家不必拘Y 我砹!
Be gone, you artless fuckwit. This is my moment.
走_ 混~|西 @是我的r刻
And thanks to the Secret Archives,
密令指示
it's the last you will ever enjoy!
@⑹悄阕钺岬r刻!
Tell me a secret, Leonardo.
R昂{多 告V我一秘密吧
What was your... earliest memory?
你最早的... 是什N?
Or better yet,
或者 Q}
your greatest fear?
你最害怕的是什N?
In my case...
ξ碚f...
the two go hand-in-hand.
@}差不多
I was...um...
我那r...
I was six months old.
我那r才六月
No-one remembers back that far.
]人能得@N小r候的事
Well, perhaps I'm unique, then.
也S我比^特e吧
- Oh.  - My mother... um...
- 好吧  - 我母H...
put me in a cradle out in the field.
е我去田里 ⑽曳旁u@Y
And a falcon flew down. I can still recall it.
一bCw了下 我得
It just perched there, looking at me
它就在那 看著我
almost as if it were trying to reveal
彷废胍揭示
some kind of mystery.
什N秘密
My mother drove it away.
母Hs走了它
Yet, as clear as that memory is,
m然我的性很好
the one thing I can never recall...
但是我唯一不得的...
is my mother's face.
就是我母H的
I can draw anything I've seen, even in passing.
我能出所有看^的|西 甚至那些D瞬即逝的
But when it comes to my mother, all I see is a void.
但每次回想我母H 都]有一丁c印象
She disappeared that night and I've been...
自哪且顾消失後 我一直...
trying to recall her face ever since.
努力回想她的幼
All men are searching for their mothers.
所有的男人都在ふ易约旱哪赣H
That's what guides you between our thighs.
所以才流B於女人的大腿之g
I pay you to pose, Vanessa.
我雇你懋模特的 瓦妮莎
Not to plumb the innermost depths of my character.
不是你砀Q探我心底的
If you expect me to bare my figure for you,
你希望我在你面前赤裸裸
I expect you to bare your soul in return.
我也希望你能ξ姨拐\`魂
So, tell me, is there nothing else you fear?
告V我吧 你最害怕什N?
Only imperfection.
不蛲昝
Maestro! Maestro!
大! 大!
You're late, Nico.
你t到了 尼科
You're late. Verrocchio's been looking for you.
是你t到了 S_吉W正找你呢
Well, he can wait. We've an experiment to conduct.
他等吧 我碜鲆
You're meant to play a principal role in it.
@少了你不行
- Come on!  - Hello.
- 戆!  - 你好
They're called breasts, Nico. Every woman possesses them.
那叫胸部 尼科 每女人都有的
Nico! That's Vanessa.
尼科! 那是瓦妮莎
She's newly liberated from the Convent of St Anthony.
她穆}安|尼修道院解放出
Now help me do this.
^臀
Climb into that harness.
上那背
Hey today,
今天
we are attempting to ascertain whether or not
我要LC明 @L~
this kite can provide the necessary wind resistance
能否提供足虻目庾枇
to support your weight.
碇文愕闹亓
Well, Maestro, what if it can't?
大 如果它不能呢?
Vanessa, do you mind just dancing about for a moment?
瓦妮莎 可以跳何?
You see? Those weighted ribbons
看了? 那些h拥慕z
allow me to calculate the strength
我能蛞虼擞算出
and direction of the wind.
L力和L向
In this case, I would say... it's about 20 knots
F在 我估算... L力大s20
and shifting...
L向...
westerly.
北方
Wait, Maestro! What if your calculations are wrong?
等等 大! f一你算e了呢?
Wait, wait, Maestro! Oh, Maestro, please, please stop!
等等 等等 大! 大 求你了 快停下!
Oh, wait, Maestro. Maestro!
等等 大 大!
Oh, my God, please!
哦 我的天哪 快停下!
Yes!
看啊!
You're flying, Nico!
你w起砹 尼科!
Maestro-o-o!
大!
It's perfect!
太完美了!
You're too high! Not so high.
太高了! e@N高
Nico!
尼科!
It works! It works, Maestro!
成功了! 成功了 大!
I never had any doubts.
我奈岩蛇^
Oh, God, I hate this place.
天哪 我@地方
What? Where else could we practice our flights
什N? 除了佛__有其他地方
but in Florence?
能我w?
Anywhere else, we'd just be burnt at the stake
要是在其他地方 我早就因此
for our efforts.
被施以火刑了
But here? I'm just another free-thinking heretic.
@耗? 我只是一思想自由的教徒
Chaos. Culture.
混沌 文化
It's all celebrated within these walls.
在@高之 所有的一切都是自由的
Florence only demands one thing of its people.
佛__λ的人民只有一要求
To be truly awake.
真正的X醒
Like that angelic vision.
此女只天上有
Don't even think about it. That's Lucrezia Donati.
e妄想了 那是R克蕾RI・多{蒂
Lorenzo de Medici's mistress. I'm well aware of who she is.
洛佐・德・美第奇的情D 我很清楚她是l
He'll break you on the wheel,
如果他抓到你在看她
if he catches you looking at her.
把你五R分频
But what if she's caught looking at me?
但如果是她在看我呢?
Bad tidings from Milan, Nico.
米m那南息 尼科
How can you tell?
你怎N知道?
That serpent on the rider's surcoat is the Biscione,
T士外套上的D案是o毒hy蛇
the Sforza family emblem.
斯福扎家族的族徽
If he was bringing good news, he'd have been dressed
如果他淼氖呛孟息 他戴上
in the more traditional red and white shield of Milan.
更鹘y的t白相g的米m徽章
Whatever the message is,
不管是什N消息
Lorenzo won't be happy with it.
洛佐都不高d的
Out!
出去!
Out! All of you!
出去! 全部出去!
Lorenzo? Lorenzo!
洛佐? 洛佐!
The Duke of Milan is dead.
米m公爵死了
- Assassinated.  - By whose hand?
- 被刺⒌  - l值?
- Visconti and two others.  - An honor killing, then.
- 威士康蒂和另外人  - 那是su\⒘
They say the Duke deflowered his niece.
他f 公爵暴了自己的侄女
Sforza was a pig of epic appetites.
斯福扎是j求不M的i
Yes, but he was our pig!
是 但他也是我的i!
I sense the Vatican's hand behind this.
我X得梵蒂是幕後黑手
The timing is just too perfect.
rC把握得太蚀_
If you're right, this upsets the balance of power in Italy, Lorenzo.
如果你是Φ @打破意大利的萘ζ胶 洛佐
Oh, by God, Becchi, this more than upsets.
哦 神啊 奇 @不HH是打破
This all but decapitates the concept
@直就是完全摧
and shits down its throat!
λ公然挑!
We need to shore up public support.
我需要取公的支持
Easter holiday is nearly upon us.
突罟假期快到了
Let's throw a carnival.
我k一嘉年A
Allow the people of Florence to celebrate
佛__的人民像c祝
the end of Lent as they do its arrival.
大S的到硪g送它的Y束
The more flamboyant the pageantry,
盛r越空前
the stronger we appear.
@得我越
We're not fucking peacocks, Giuliano.
我不是垤乓的孔雀 朱利Z
Carnival is all well and good,
嘉年A是不e
but if it has no teeth behind it,
但如果]有大的後台
we might as well slit our own throats.
我同邮窃谧匀缤
Are you frightened?
你害怕?
No, Most Holy Father.
不 尊敬的教皇
Lying is a sin, my dear boy.
fe是一N罪 我的孩子
It separates us from God's grace.
它我失去神的恩
Yes, I'm frightened.
是的 我害怕
But that's also a lie, isn't it?
@也是e Π?
At least, a partial one.
至少 不全是真
A venial sin, perhaps.
也S@是可赦之罪
So...
那N...
which statement is correct?
哪一N回答才是真的?
Hm?
嗯?
Speak, child.
f啊 孩子
Don't you want to enter heaven?
y道你不想上天堂?
The proper answer would be...
正_的回答是...
Please! His Holiness has forbidden any visitors.
留步! 教皇禁止任何人打_
Our men succeeded, Your Grace!
我的人成功了 大人!
Sforza is dead.
斯福扎死了
Florence is ripe for the picking, Your Eminence.
是r候拿下佛__了 教皇大人
Trust me.
相信我
You know this how?
槭颤N@Nf?
Because I have an agent within Lorenzo's ranks.
洛佐身有我的人
The Medicis are throwing a carnival,
美第奇家族要ek一嘉年A
in a pathetic bid to win the people's favor.
想借此碲A得人民的支持
They're weak, Your Holiness.
他不堪一 陛下
This is your chance to strike.
@是您一e拿下他的好C
Not mine, Nephew.
不是我 侄子
The Lord's.
是上帝
There is another reason for haste.
有一件事要告V您
The Turk has arrived in Florence.
土耳其人已到佛__了
He's after the Book of Leaves.
他在找~之
I am truly sorry.
真的很抱歉
Why?
槭颤N?
Because you can't have heard this.
因槟懵到的太多了
Do you have the plans for the colombina or not?
你浜螟子表演了?
We do.
是的
And they're breathtaking.
十分@G
Then produce these miraculous renderings
那就把@些神奇的效果展F出
and let us evaluate them.
我u估一下
Unfortunately...
很z憾...
I can't.
我不能
Because they don't exist!
因樗不存在!
By God, if you think you can defraud
神啊 如果你X得你能欺_
the House of Medici...
美第奇家族...
No, no, no, they do exist, I promise you!
不 不 不 它存在 我向你保C!
They're in this chest.
它在@箱子Y
- Open it.  - It's locked.
- 打_  - 它被i上了
Well, then, I'll take my sword to it.
好啊 那我用ε_它
The chest is rigged to explode
如果行打_@箱子的
if anyone tampers with it.
它就爆炸
Are you mad?
你了?
Why would anyone engineer such an infernal contrivance?
怎N有人造出@N可怕的l明?
To protect my ideas, obviously.
然是榱吮Ｗo我的意
Gentlemen, Leonardo Da Vinci.
先生 @位是R昂{多・_芬奇
Ah, I've heard of you.
啊 我f^你
They say you're quite the free-thinker.
他f你是自由思想家
- You're late.  - Grape.
- 你硗砹  - 沓葡萄
So! The First Citizen of Florence
好! 佛__L官
is desperate for us to fashion him a colombina.
渴求我o他u造出一b子
"Desperate" is a strong word.
"渴求"f得太^了
And yet it happens to be the word I used.
可我f的是事
But let's review.
我回想一下
Every Easter, a grand procession makes its way
每年突罟 佛__的街^
through the streets of Florence,
都有浩大的[行伍
terminating at the cathedral.
走向大教堂
Why do you insist on stating
你槭颤N非要f@些
what every child of three already knows?
B三q小孩都知道的U?
Why do you insist on interrupting me?
你槭颤N非要打辔?
I have a methodology. We can follow it.
我有我的方法 你可以我的
Or we can flail about.
或者咱也可以打一架
I'll take your silence as a vote for the former. Onward.
不f我就默J你我的了 那我^m
At the culmination of mass, a mechanical dove,
在人群上空 一bC械子
the colombina, is flown from the altar on a wire.
也就是@只子 е烤 穆}上
Out into the public square it soars.
翱翔到V錾峡
It ignites a cart full of fireworks.
c燃一的花
The Republic celebrates, they don masks.
群_始gc 戴上面具
They engage in drunken revelry. Now...
喝酒狂g...
For years, the House of Medici has contracted
啄 美第奇家族一直在l
with inferior workshops to produce said ceremonial dove.
低劣的工坊u造@x式子
But, this year,
但是今年
if I am to understand the politics afoot,
不出我所料的
the same shoddy pageantry
@N低劣的情景
just won't do.
不再l生了
No-one's carped about our dove before.
]有人ξ的子吹毛求疵
To call your previous efforts 'a dove' is to insult the entire avian class.
你管那叫"子" 直是B的侮辱
Enough! Just show us the damn thing.
蛄! 快o我展示你@破玩意吧
All right.
好吧
That is but a quarter-scale model.
@是四分之一比例模型
It's a thing of beauty, I'll grant you that.
@真的很漂亮啊
Yes, and it can be yours for 30 florins.
]e 30弗_林 你就能ё吡
- 30?  - Yeah.
- 30弗_林?  - ]e
The contract stated 12.
合同上的是12弗_林
That was for a bird that needed a guide wire.
那NB需要K子恳才行
This miracle requires no such handicap.
@t不需要那N|西
Your work is impressive.
你的作品令人印象深刻
But the price is too steep.
但是rX太不合理了
- 30 florins is a bargain.  - 30 florins is sodomy!
- 30弗_林很便宜啊  - 30弗_林直是劫!
Perhaps I should be negotiating
或S我
with your older brother instead.
和你的哥哥r
For God's sake, Becchi,
天啊 奇
just pay the degenerate and be done with it.
付Xo@v民 so了Y@事算了
You win, artista.
算你A了 g家
As is customary with commissions,
按照佣金的T例
we shall pay half now and half upon completion.
我先付一半定金 完工後再付另一半
While we're on the subject of commissions,
既然f到佣金...
I'm told that there's an open one to paint Lucrezia Donati.
我f 你在找人oR克蕾RI・多{蒂肖像
Lorenzo's mistress.
洛佐的情D
Stick to your whirligigs and parlor tricks, Da Vinci.
Ｐ撵赌愕耐嬉夂托“虬 _芬奇
Take a lesson from Icarus.
想想伊卡洛斯的下
So, tell me...
告V我吧...
is there nothing else you fear?
你最害怕什N?
Are you all right, Leonardo?
你]事吧 R昂{多?
It was just a nightmare, Andrea.
只是噩 安德Y
You have them all too frequently.
你噩糇龅锰l繁了
I'm having some issues with my mathematics, that's all.
我在算上遇到了c} H此而已
Issues?
}?
I'm not sure...
我不知道...
that the colombina will be flightworthy by Easter.
突罟前 能不能造出砟欠N子
- But the model...  - Was a model.
- 但那模型...  - 那只是模型
Once I scale up the dimensions,
我按比例放大的之後
the calculations don't hold. It's annoying!
算就出}了 真┤
Smoking opium won't help matters.
你抽f片]有用
- It clears my head.  - It clouds it.
- 至少能我清醒  - 它只能你糊T
What are you, my nursemaid? I think too much. All right?
你是l? 我的保姆? 我要想的事情太多了 好?
I need to dull my thoughts or I'll be eviscerated by them.
我需要糊T一下 不然我就要了
I would have thought that you would have
我X得你F在
understood that by now!
明白了吧!
The tears of the poppy have medicinal properties.
f片有用r值
- The priests in Egypt...  - We are not in Egypt.
- 埃及的祭司...  - 我不在埃及
And you are no priest.
你也不是祭司
You have a gift, Leo.
你很有天x R昂
A kind of...genius...
可以f是... 天才...
the likes of which I've never seen.
我奈匆^像你@拥娜
Because of that, people will always seek to destroy you.
正因如此 人想方O法地消缒
Please...
拜...
don't aid them in their endeavor.
不要在自我 如他所了
- How much for the starlings?  - Six denari apiece.
- @些椋B多少X?  - 每只六~X
I'll give you two soldi for the lot.
o你摄~X 我都要了
Are you trying to offend me?
你在侮辱我?
No, if I was trying to offend you,
]有 要是我想侮辱你的
I'd comment on the scent of fecal matter
我f你的臀部後
wafting from your hindquarters.
熘S便物
Do you want the soldi or not?
摄~X到底行不行?
They're my last. I'm bored.
只有@N多X 不要就算了
No, I'm not interested in the birds.
不 我不想ё哌@些B
Just open the cage on my say-so.
我的指]把\子打_
He's obsessed with flight. He studies them for inspiration.
他w行感d趣 他想通^B找`感
Now.
_
Well? Did you see what you were hoping to?
恩? 如看到什N了?
For one of my soldi back, I just might tell you.
我一~X 我就告V你
All right. Tell me.
好吧 告V我
I saw an idiot who doesn't know how to haggle.
我看到一傻瓜不知道怎诱r
Look, Nico. There she is again.
看那 尼科 她又砹
Look at her with Lorenzo.
她和洛佐在一起
Everyone pretending the two of them aren't fucking.
所有人都b得不知道扇松线^床
- Isn't that your father?  - Crown Prince of parasites.
- 那不是你父H?  - 他像寄生x一
He serves as Lorenzo's notary.
o洛佐公C人
Come on, Nico, let's stir the pot a little.
戆 尼科 咱去狒[
Your Magnificence!
殿下!
My name is Leonardo Da Vinci. Perhaps you've heard of me?
我叫R昂{多・_芬奇 您可能f^我?
I am designing your Easter colombina.
我在槟O突罟的子
Oh, yes.
噢
You're the eccentric that Verrocchio employs.
你就是S_吉Wl虻哪怪人
I'm an artist, yes, and an anatomist
我是g家 解剖W家
and an engineer of some note.
是工程
"Extortionist" is the word I recall using.
我得我Q呼你"劫匪"吧
I drive a stiff bargain, it's true.
我rr很吝 ]e
But the fact is, I have designed
但事上 我O了
a more ambitious series of devices
S多更宏大的b置
that I know your percipient mind
我知道您慧眼R珠
will take an interest in.
一定感d趣
Move along, vermin.
躲_c 混蛋
Another time.
下次吧
Perhaps.
也S
I'm wounded, Nico.
我心了 尼科
I need wine.
我要喝酒
How goes business, Zoroaster?
生意怎N _斯德?
Execrable, since the Duke's demise.
自墓爵死後 一直糟透了
These are dark times for Florence.
佛__密
Case in point. Those mercenaries flooding into town.
比如那些涌M城的l虮
If war does break out,
假如真的爆l
they'll be the only ones gainfully employed.
他是唯一能X的人
Speaking of employment,
f到X
a two-headed calf, stillborn on Zitto's farm.
托的r鲇须b牛匍L了^ 出生就死了
I can procure it, if you like, for your medical studies.
如果你tW研究用的 我可以o你弄
The last corpse was decomposing by the time I took a scalpel to it.
上一次你送淼哪蔷企w都腐了
Grave-robbing is like fishmongering.
挖掘墓和捕~一
You're at the mercy of the day's catch.
每次都要靠\
Come on. A boar sausage?
吃ic?
You know damn well that I am a vegetarian.
你知道我是素食主x者
- So I keep hoping to corrupt you.  - Oh, I'm corruptible.
- 所以我才M力腐化你  - 噢 我很容易腐化的
I just prefer not to eat anything with eyes.
我只是不想吃L眼睛的|西
- Potatoes have eyes.  - Fuck off, Nico!
- 土豆也L眼睛  - L吧 尼科!
Maestro!
大!
May I model for you again?
我能再槟做模特?
No-one looks at my form as you do.
]有人像您一友酃猹特
No-one looks at any form as I do.
我看什N都眼光特
Go peddle your wares with Botticelli.
想推N商品去博蒂切利那吧
He's an easy mark.
他容易上
Model? That boy's nothing but a hustler
模特? 那孩子只是_子
and an artless one at that.
而且_技很差
But pleasing to the eye, nonetheless.
但他眼神招人喜
Piss.
呸
Here. Have a gander at these.
看一眼@
My latest venture.
我的最新酆
They're called tarot cards.
@是塔_牌
They're used to divine fortunes.
用碚疾访\
Here. Pick one, Nico. We'll see if it squares with your temperament.
戆 尼科 抽一 看看是否和你性情一致
- Funny. It's a trick.  - Is it?
- 有意思 是魔g吧  - 是?
Or am I simply channeling the powers of The Ancients?
也S是h古力量和我的贤呢?
How many women has that line worked on, Zo?
你用@_^多少女孩 _?
A respectable amount. Thank you very much.
一大堆女孩 xxF
And a goodly number of gentlemen, as well.
我也_^很多男的
But a card can symbolize not just one's temperament,
塔_牌不止能象徵性情
but one's fate.
能撞访\
Do you dare see yours?
你敢占卜你的?
Tell me. Don't hold back.
告V我 e[m
This one...
@...
represents sacrifice.
代表祭I
A suspension between life and death and then perhaps...
在生c死之g游x 然後可能...
a great awakening.
迎ゴ蟮挠X醒
I'm an idiot.
我是傻瓜
Those mercenaries. Florence has no army of its own.
那些l虮 佛__]有自己的
So they're here to sell their muscle. Right?
所以那些虮才碣u命 Π?
But what if there was a more lucrative way to traffic in the Republic's unease?
但要是有更加有利可D的方法呢?
- Like what?  - I should promote myself
- 比如?  - 我f自己...
as a military engineer, not a painter.
去做事工程 而不是家
War has always been the handmaiden of progress.
是可以推影l展
If I want to explore my ideas,
如果我想^m探索下去
I just need to cloak them in the guise of Florence's defense.
我只要以防R佛__榻杩诰涂梢粤
Why are the officers of the night bothering that man?
槭颤N那些夜巡L官在找那人的麻?
He's a Turk, a heathen. Isn't that reason enough?
他是土耳其教徒 原因不蛎黠@?
No.
不要管
No, this isn't your fight, Leo.
@不P你的事 R昂
When's that ever stopped me?
@N原因能阻止我?
What seems to be the trouble here?
l生什N事了?
Go back to your sketchbook, scribbler.
致致锶 的
This isn't your concern.
@]你的事
You see, unfortunately, um...
你看 很不幸 恩...
I have this character flaw
我有N癖好
that compels me to intervene whenever stupidity rears its head, so...
遇到不平的事我就忍不住要插手 所以...
You see? Cos that was stupid.
看到了? 太笨了
Cos your man's grip was too loose
因槟阄盏锰了
and now he finds himself
F在你低^看r
staring down this handsome spada da filo.
才lF自己把G了
Even more stupidity.
@更笨了
Cos if you'd just asked around,
你去打打
anyone will tell you that I'm ambidextrous
所有人都f我p手`巧
and perfectly capable of fighting two or...
可以p地同rΩ...
even three men simultaneously.
甚至三人
Bully someone else, Dragonetti.
欺e人去吧 德拉戈奈蒂
You've made a serious miscalculation tonight, artista.
你今晚失算了 g家
It wouldn't be the first time.
反正又不是第一次了
- Are you all right, sir?  - I'm more than all right.
- 你好吧 先生?  - 我很好
I am a son of Earth and Starry Heaven.
我是大地c星空之子
I return to Constantinople the day after tomorrow.
後天我就要回君士坦丁堡了
But I am staying at the Inn of the Black Swan.
我住在黑天Z旅店
Come see me before I leave...
我x_之前硪我...
Maestro.
大
A bit weird.
有c怪
What did he give you?
他o你的是什N?
A tip, I think.
我X得 是提示
It was her mother.
那是她
The same arse, very different faces
屁股一 可大不一
and, when I realized, I did a little sip on her tit.
然後 我J出碇後 小吸了下她奶^
Take him, Nico. Jesus. He'll never make it home alone.
扶著他 尼科 天啊 他一人回不了家的
Are you sure, Maestro? It's after curfew and there are bound to be rogues about.
你_定 大? 已宵禁了 也S有I什N的
- Then I'll fit right in. Go!  - Listen, Leo.
- 正好m合我 去吧!  - 著 YW
What?
什N?
I didn't deal you the Hanged Man. That was all you.
倒吊人那卡 不是我特意弄的 是你自己x的
It was an omen. It was just like the two-headed calf.
那是A兆 不是什N好兆^
No, I don't believe in omens.
行了 我不信什NA兆
No. No, this is you. Go.
行了行了 你才信 走吧
Go!
快走!
I know it's you, Dragonetti.
我知道是你 德拉戈奈蒂
Did you not learn your lesson earlier?
之前的教你]接受啊?
Ah.
啊
I guess you did learn.
看砟憬邮芰
That's enough.
可以了
I should have known.
我早知道
People are talking about you.
大家δ阕h
And not in a positive light.
就是]什N好ur
I couldn't care less what they're saying about me.
我牟辉诤e人怎Nf我
I care!
我在乎!
I'll not have you tarnishing our family's name
我不能你玷污家族的名
with your flippant tone and your vulgar attempts at self-promotion.
油腔滑{ 自我宣 e止p佻
Perhaps you should disown me, then.
那跟我xPM好了
You're my first-born.
你是我的L子
And much as I may wish to disavow you,
就算我想跟你x父子PS
our reputations are intertwined.
我的名是mp一起
First-born?
L子?
You say that as if...
你f得倒像是...
My wife, Margherita...
我妻子 格特...
bore me a son this past week.
上周槲疑了鹤
A legitimate heir.
一合法^承人
Well, my condolences to him.
哦 向他表示哀悼
I wonder how long it will take him to curse his lineage.
不知道他什Nr候才_始痛恨自己的血y
As a bastard, your rank within the social order has been rigidly defined.
你不^是私生子 社地位就]什N可商量的了
You should endeavor to remain within it.
你最好老地接受自己的地位
Stay away from the Medicis, Leonardo.
x美第奇家族hc R昂{多
- I'll not warn you again.  - I'll wager you will.
- @是最後一次警告了  - 省省吧
Why do you have to make this so difficult?
你槭颤N跟我作?
It's my nature! I see things as they are,
@是我的天性! 我看到事物的本|
not as they might be.
而不是表象
You...
你...
are a petty man.
心胸M隘
And... you will never achieve greatness.
你... ]可能有所作
Where as I...
而我...
I already have.
我已有所作榱
You're kneeling in a dungeon.
你F在跪在地牢Y
About to be hit again and again.
要^m挨打
By men who know how to hit.
打你的都是中好手
That's what you've achieved, Leonardo.
你就@c作榱 R昂{多
Beat him for another hour,
再打一小r
then toss him back onto the street with the rest of the garbage.
然後跟其他垃圾一起扔到街上去
Hold out the scribbler's hand.
按住@小子的手
To be fair, you actually look more wretched than I, so...
f真的 你看起肀任疫要可z了 所以...
well done.
你害
Perhaps you should see a physician.
是去看看t生吧
I'm fine.
我]事
Oh, they're executing a Jew today.
噢 今天有q太人要被g死
Apparently, they caught him breaking into the book shop on the Via Dei Librai.
很@然 他抓到他J入了西・_街的一家店
It should be good sport.
是不e的盛
I'm not sure a man's death should be characterized as sport.
我不X得一人的死可以被Q槭
This fucking spot is too sunny. Can't we move over into the shade?
@地方太窳 我Q鳇c的地方吧?
- No.  - Why?
- 不行  - 槭颤N?
Because every morning, at precisely this time,
因槊刻煸缟 就@r候
Lucrezia Donati comes to this exact spot to purchase...
R克蕾RI・多{蒂都磉@YI...
flowers.
r花
There.
瞧
She's appealing, I'll grant you that, but...
她很迷人 @c我同 但是...
I'd rather bed that old toothless hag over there.
我肯跟那]牙老巫婆睡一X
Now you're just being contrary.
你@偬
It takes no great skill to fuck a pretty face.
干漂亮女人不需要什N技巧
But a truly ugly woman, that actually requires discipline
但要干h女人 才真正是挑
and, let me tell you, my friend, done right,
我f 朋友 搞得好的
a transcendent experience.
那可真是欲M欲死
Nico, run this over to her.
尼科 把@o她送去
Make sure she knows where it's come from.
_保她知道是l送的
What the devil are you up to, Leo?
YW 你到底在想些什N?
She wants to speak with you.
她要跟你f
Uh-huh? Well, tell her I'm busy.
啊哈 告V她 我忙著呢
You're seriously not turning her down?
致锊怀岽蜩F?
Tell her, Nico. Timing is all.
去跟她f 尼科 rC未到
He can't right now.
他F在]空
Behold, a criminal in our midst!
看哪 我中的一罪犯!
A Jew, no less!
q太人 又是q太人!
Watch him dance! Watch him dangle!
看著他跳! 看著他晃!
Bring your fruit and small stones!
拿好你的水果和石子!
God protect the Republic of Florence!
上帝保佑佛__共和!
I am a son of Earth and Starry Heaven.
我是大地c星空之子
I am thirsty.
我渴了
Please, give me something to drink
求你了 挠之泉中
from the Fountain of Memory.
取水o我喝
Are you all right, Maestro?
大 你]事吧?
I need to leave.
我得走了
Is there a foreigner staying here, a Turkish man?
@Y住著外人? 一土耳其人?
He said you could find him at the Roman ruins,
他f你可以到_RzE去找他
north of town.
就在城北
Will you smoke with me, Da Vinci?
_芬奇 和我一起抽吧?
Well, that depends on what's in the pipe.
那要看管Yb了什N
History is a lie that has been honed like a weapon
v史就如同武器一般
by people who have suppressed the truth.
被那些意欲掩w真相的人肆意改 只剩e言
Centuries from now, your own history
装倌赆 你自己的v史
will also be suppressed.
也被掩w
How could you possibly know that?
你怎N可能知道?
You have heard the phrase "Time is a river"?
你^@句? "rg是一l河流"
What most fail to grasp
所不槿酥的是
is that the river is circular.
河流是一循h
One man's death...
一人死去...
opens a doorway to the birth of the next.
榱硪人的降生敞_了大T
I saw a man executed today.
我今天看到一人被g死了
He said something to me.
他ξ艺f了些
- I am...  - A son of Earth
- 我是...  - 大地c
and Starry Heaven.
星空之子
I am thirsty.
我渴了
Please, give me something to drink
求你了 挠之泉中
from the Fountain of Memory.
取水o我喝
It is an invocation.
@是一句\~
A way for members of our fraternity
我同族之g
to recognize one another.
互相辨J的暗Z
I'm not a member of your fraternity.
我又不是你一族
Are you sure?
你_定?
This temple was once a place of worship
@座R宇曾是一宗教的Y拜堂
for a religion that originated
而@宗教 v史比基督教
long before Christ.
更加久h
We are known as the Sons of Mithras.
我被Q槊芴乩(波斯太神)之子
Much of what you call 'progress'
大多的所^的"M步"
has simply been a matter of remembering what was once forgotten.
不^都是些一度失落的回
This knowledge was set down
@些知R都被在
in a compendium known as the Book of Leaves.
一本被Q"~之"的典籍Y
Recently, certain clues have surfaced regarding the Book's location.
最近 P於@本所在之的NN索 逐u浮出水面
Avraham ben Yosef was following those clues
阿趵罕・本・尤瑟夫被逮捕K死前
when he was apprehended and put to death.
就一直在追み@些索
Perhaps you have heard of the Secret Archives the Vatican has assembled?
梵蒂的密令 不知你是否有所耳?
Its curator is a man called Lupo Mercuri.
密令的管理人 叫R珀・梅克Y
A fallen son of Mithras.
密特拉族人的叛徒
Where we seek to disseminate and preserve knowledge.
我追求的是鞑ズ捅Ｗo知R
They seek to alter and suppress it.
而他篡改知R 限制知R鞑
I still... I still don't understand
我是... 我是不明白
what any of this has to do with me.
@些跟我有什NPS
What do you know... about your mother?
你δ隳赣H... 有什N印象?
Almost nothing.
缀]有
She... she disappeared.
她... 她失了
- She was a servant girl.  - She was a slave.
- 她是女W  - 她是奴`
Taken from Constantinople against her will.
被行木士坦丁堡ё吡
Do you remember...
你是否得...
an incident that occurred in your childhood?
童年r代遭遇^的什N事故?
You have suppressed it.
你一直褐七@段
I was a boy in Vinci.
我小r候在芬奇
I'd been sent to fetch some sheep that had wandered off.
被派去ふG失的羊群
I found a cave.
我lF了一山洞
I was scared to go inside, but...
我不敢M去 但...
But I was curious.
但我很好奇
So I ventured in.
是冒UM去了
The next hours... are blank.
然後的事情... 我想不起砹
I remember...
我得...
stumbling out.
踉地走出
My hands and face...
我的手上上...
were covered in blood.
都沾M了血
And somehow...
不知何故...
I knew it wasn't my own.
我清楚那不是我的血
One day...
有一天...
you will sip from the Fountain of Memory...
你下之泉的水...
and learn more of what occurred in that cave.
想起更多你在洞中的v
When that day comes, we will meet again.
到那一天 我再
What do I do till then?
在那之前我怎N做?
Search for the Book of Leaves.
ふ"~之"
Fate has chosen you, Leonardo.
R昂{多 命\x窳四
- I don't believe in fate.  - Then believe in yourself.
- 我不相信命\  - 那就相信你自己
Well, where do I start my search, then?
好吧 那N我暮翁_始ふ?
With the hanged man, the seat of the soul.
慕g死的人入手 撵`魂深入手
He's already opened the door for you.
他已槟愦蜷_了一扇T
And my mother?
那我母H?
She will be for you on the other side.
她⒃诒硕说却著你
All you have to do...
你需要做的就是...
is enter.
M入那扇T
Maestro? Maestro? Can you hear me?
大? 大? 能到?
Maestro!
大!
We've been looking for you since last night. What happened?
我淖蛲砭驮谡夷 l生了什N事?
The Turk was here.
那土耳其人r在@
There was... there was a statue.
@涸先有... 有一座雕像
An altar.
是祭
Must have weighed a ton.
得有一重
This place has been empty for centuries, Leo.
YW @地方都荒U很久了
Maestro, the Officers of the Night have been searching for you.
大 夜巡官一直在找你
They say Lorenzo Medici himself has asked for you.
他f洛佐・美第奇本人要接你
Leonardo di ser Piero...
你是R昂{多・迪・瑟・皮耶_...
Da Vinci.
_芬奇
I am told you are my notary's bastard son.
f你是我公CT的私生子
I am.
]e
I'm also told that you are a troublemaker,
我f你是惹事精
you are arrogant, impolitic...
傲慢自大 o尊L...
and utterly incapable of keeping your opinions to yourself.
完全不懂得保留自己的想法
Arrogance implies that I exaggerate my own worth.
傲慢自大 f明我F大了自己的r值
I don't.
我]有
My mistress, Lucrezia,
我的女人 R克蕾RI
seems to think that you have a singular talent for portraiture.
似乎X得你有非凡的L天x
She insisted that you and none other be the one to...
她猿终J 除了你 ]有人能...
capture her beauty.
捕捉到她的美貌
I'd say she has a discerning eye, then.
那我要f她有pR人的慧眼
A warning, sir.
L官 o您警醒
The man has a reputation for taking many commissions, but finishing few.
@砘镏荒缅X不只钍浅隽嗣的
I wrestle with details. I bore easily.
我常斟酌 所以容易
Call it a character flaw.
@算是性格缺陷吧
Well, with this commission,
接了@份活
you'd be wise to overcome it.
你最好能克服@缺陷
When it comes to Miss Donati,
要多{蒂小姐的
boredom is the last thing I fear.
我^Σ感到
I'll have your father draw up a contract then.
那我就你父H起草合同啦
Sir, if I may, I have a few other designs...
L官 不知v不v 我有些其他O...
I have some designs that I think you might be interested in.
有些O 或S你感d趣
This will greatly increase your gunner's rate of firepower.
@O大地增你手下炮手的火力
So, while the top rack's being fired,
上拥呐诩馨l射的同r
the rack below that one can be loaded
下拥呐诩芸梢匝b填
and the rack below that one is allowed to cool.
再下拥呐诩芫陀rg冷s
The cannons are arranged in a fan, which...
炮管呈扇形排_ 能...
- That will be enough. Da Vinci.   - This is an armored cart.
- 蛄 _芬奇  - @是一vb甲
Propulsion is achieved by two men, who are housed within.
由擅藏在其中的士兵推
They operate cranks, which rotate the wheels.
通^D忧柄 榆前M
Cannons can be mounted around the perimeter of the cart.
炮管可以安置在的四周
It's a flying machine.
@是架w行C器
It's modeled after the articulated wings of a bat.
仿自蝙蝠q接式的翅膀
Madness. If man were meant to fly...
了 如果人要能w的...
He would have been born with wings. Yes.
那生砭驮有翅膀 ]e
But a similar assertion could have been made prior to the invention of gunpowder
但是人l明火 以及其他的一些l明之前 甚至lF火之前
or any other invention conceived since fire.
也有人有似的喟
I believe man will fly and I base this assumption
我相信人能征服{天 我之所以@NJ
on the fact that God has blessed us
是因樯系劢o了我思想
with minds that are capable of imagining it.
能蛳胂竦拇竽X
Anything that can be dreamt of will eventually be built.
人所粝氲囊磺 最K都能F
Anyone who says otherwise is a fool.
不同意我的人 都是傻子
What exactly do you propose?
你到底想质颤N?
I wish to be employed...
我想受雇...
as a military engineer.
成檐事工程
I am a humanist, Da Vinci.
_芬奇 我是人道主x者
I have no interest in waging war.
我o意l
And yet your humanism is precisely why war will happen.
但正是由於你的人道主x 才l生
Florence has no standing army.
弗__]有常滠
Nor does Rome.
_R也]有
Necessarily...
出於需要...
you've both made alliances with states that do.
你都和碛谐滠的家Y了盟
Florence with Milan,
弗洛_和米mY盟
and Rome with Naples.
_R和{普勒斯Y盟
Sforza's death has up-ended the game board.
斯福扎遇刺 覆了[蛞t
You need weapons of your own, Your Magnificence.
殿下 您需要凫蹲约旱奈淦
I will give you a modest stipend.
我o你一P合m的M
To see whether these...
看@些能否...
contraptions of yours can actually be realized.
你的@些奇妙b置能否最KF
- Shall we say 100 florins?  - 50.
- o100佛_林如何?  - 50
If you haggle any further, I'll cut out your tongue.
你再rr 我就割下你的舌^
As you say, sir.
您f了算 L官
Thank you.
xx
You used Lucrezia to gain access to me, didn't you?
你利用R克蕾RI斫咏我 Π?
I utilize any device at my disposal,
我利用一切手段
in order to realize my goals.
F我的目
Clever,
明
but I'd caution you not to be too clever around me.
但我警告你 替我只 e明^^了
Clockwork loses its luster,
l的炔造
once one glimpses the gears beneath its face.
只要被看穿 也就失去魅力
Point taken.
您f得
Is there a problem?
有什N}?
None at all, sir.
]有 L官
Good day.
再
- Congratulations, Leonardo.  - Word travels fast.
- 祝R你 R昂{多  - 消息鞯谜婵
Ah, there are no secrets in Florence.
弗洛_哪有什N秘密
How the devil did you do it?
你到底怎N做到的呢?
Oh, he played on a woman's vanity.
哦 他利用了一女人的s
Your stratagem has become clear, you bastard.
你混蛋 你的\我看得一清二楚
A bastard of the highest order.
他是一流的混蛋
Ha! Drink up everybody.
哈! 大伙乾杯
Then get back to work. We've got a colombina to build!
之後回去工作 我得做只焰呢!
The Jew that was hanged, I want you to unearth his body.
你去把被g死q太人的企w挖出
I need to examine it.
我要z查z查
And my compensation?
o我什N蟪?
Well, that depends how fresh the corpse is.
得看企w成什N恿
Ah, well, then, I'd best get digging.
那我最好F在就_挖
Ah, here's the Pazzi clan.
帕a家族砹
With their schemer Francesco and old man Jacopo.
有他的\家弗朗西斯科和老男人雅各布
Probably the oldest family in Florence,
可能是佛__最老的家族
definitely the most ornery.
但^κ堑匚蛔畹偷
The Pazzi family entrusts Lorenzo de Medici
帕a家族委洛佐・德・美第奇
with this new fire,
⑦@束新火
struck on stones from the Church of the Holy Sepulcher.
插在}墓大教堂的石座上
As is our right.
以行使我的嗔
Granted to our ancestor for his actions
行使我祖先在第一次十字|征r
during the First Crusade.
所@得的嗔
The colombina is about to fly.
焰即翱翔
Welcome, all of you, into God's home.
g迎你所有人淼缴系壑家
The flames of the phoenix suit you well.
P凰的火焰和你很配
Tell me, truly,
老告V我
are you always this wistful with the whores you bed?
你和你上床的妓女 都@N念念不忘?
Oh, you are no whore, Signora.
哦 你不是妓女 夫人
We need not continue this pretence any longer, Miss Donati.
]必要再b下去了 多{蒂小姐
I knew it was you from the moment you approached me.
哪憬咏我的一_始我就知道是你
How did you know?
你怎N知道的?
I sketched you.
我^你
Your features, your form, your bearing.
一A一笑 一右混o 一言一行
The more salient question...
更重要的是...
is why would a noblewoman
楹胃哔F如你
risk her reputation on a lowly artisan?
s不惜自名u委身於一低v的呢?
Well, isn't that the point of a carnival?
@不是狂g的意x?
To pretend, for a night, that you're someone you're not.
b作你不是你自己 然後一夜L流
No, I think there's more to it than that, yeah.
不 我X得不止@
Tell me, then.
那fo我
You were intrigued by my sketch.
你被我的迷住了
Yeah, so...
所以...
You felt that it captured an aspect of yourself
你感X它勾勒出了你的另一面
that remains hidden from your husband,
@是你的丈夫 你的情人洛佐
and from your lover, Lorenzo.
都]有lF的
The only time you see this aspect...
而你也只是在...
is on the rare occasions
照R子的r候
that you glimpse yourself in the mirror,
才看到自己的另一面
and you find a stranger staring back at you.
R中的你 彷芬陌生人 回看著自己
You knew I'd seek you out, then.
你知道我再把你找出
Well...
哈...
Hey, I try to work out what motivates people
嘿 我著先lF人行榈C
and then I proceed accordingly.
然後就水推舟
You manipulate them.
你掌控他
No. I prefer to think of it as gently
不 我更意看做是 稍微地
redirecting their trajectories.
把他重新找回自己
Lorenzo was quite taken with your designs.
洛佐δ愕脑O很感d趣
Well, may I see one of these marvels?
我可以看一下@些奇E?
What is it?
@是什N?
It's a device for slowing one's rate of descent.
@是一p慢下降速度的b置
- Oh.  - Yeah.
- 哦  - 嗯
And under what circumstances would I possibly have use for this?
那我什Nr候才可能用到它呢?
Say that you were trapped in a fortress.
比方f你被困在堡狙Y
- A fortress?  - A fortress that had been breached.
- 堡?  - 被攻陷的堡
You could strap yourself into this...
你可以@在身上...
and you'd safely float down to freedom.
就能安全落地 重@自由
Oh, thank goodness.
哦 xx老天
It would appear Lorenzo's interest in you was justified.
y怪洛佐你@N感d趣
But tell me.
不^告V我
I have risked my reputation by sleeping with you.
我冒著身∶裂的U和你同床
You've risked more.
你付出了更大的代r
Perhaps even death.
f不定是生命
And to what do you ascribe my reckless behavior, then?
我@N不一切 你X得是槭颤N?
Don't be absurd.
e_玩笑了
You saw me, you drew me, you fell in love.
^目y忘 眉描香 日思夜想
It's as simple as that.
就@N
Add in the fact that I am forbidden fruit...
事上我就是禁果
and your fate was sealed.
你命中注定凵衔
You're the third person this week to lecture me on fate.
你是@星期第三跟我f命\的人
Well, perhaps it's time you started listening.
也S@正是你的r候
Now...
F在...
Fuck me again, Leonardo.
再和我做一次 R昂{多
This time, remember...
@次 好了...
you're not the only one capable of manipulation.
你不是唯一一有掌控嗟娜
The Secret Archives are open
@密令只
only to his Holiness' closest advisors.
教皇最H近的_放
For obvious reasons, we can't have you parading through the front door.
@然 我不能你M前面的T了
Ah.
啊
How rude of me.
真是失Y了
I promised you your payment first.
我答^要先o你蟪
I take it you're satisfied?
你M意了?
Your Eminence,
陛下
I bring news from Florence.
我姆鹆__砹讼息
Get on with it, then.
那就快cf
A new player has entered the stage.
有新人出F了
An artist known as Leonardo Da Vinci.
一叫做R昂{多・_芬奇的
The Medicis have employed him to design siege weapons.
美第奇家族雇他O攻城武器
Artists are as common as court jesters.
就跟m廷弄臣一悠胀
I see no reason why this news should concern us.
我看不出@消息哪YPS到我
This artist is different. His ideas are...
@不一 他的想法都...
unusual,
不同こ
revolutionary.
富有革新意x
My agent in Florence.
@是我在佛__的人
You trust your intelligence to a woman?
你相信一女人的情?
When one seeks to convey a message,
要鬟f情r
I prefer to use vessels others would readily dismiss.
我更意x袢菀妆缓鲆的人
If I am not mistaken, you are Lupo Mercuri,
要是我]看e 你就是R珀・梅克Y
Curator of the Secret Archives.
密令的管理人
- What of it?  - It may interest you to know
- @有什NPS?  - 你也S有d趣
that Da Vinci has made contact...
_芬奇已接|^了...
with the Turk.
那土耳其人
He's searching for something called the Book of Leaves.
他在找一叫"~之"的|西
It would appear the Turk has found a new champion.
似乎土耳其人找到了新的守o神
Continue watching him.
^mO他
See if he can be co-opted.
看能不能收n他
And if he can't?
要是不能呢?
Then Da Vinci will be consumed
那_芬奇⑾萑
in the fiery sorrows of hell
峥值牡鬲z
along with the rest of God's enemies.
如同上帝的橙艘